<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The first man, or, A short discourse of Adams state viz., 1. of his being made a living soul, 2. of the manner of his fall / by J.G.</title>
            <author>Greene, John, Master of Arts.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 50KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B23728</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12071987</idno>
  <idno type="VID">196804</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240954345</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing G1821</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">12071987</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B23728)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 196804)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 238:E55, no 15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The first man, or, A short discourse of Adams state viz., 1. of his being made a living soul, 2. of the manner of his fall / by J.G.</title>
                  <author>Greene, John, Master of Arts.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 21 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Benjamin Allen ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1643.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to John Greene.  Cf. BLC.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Thomason Collection, British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Adam --  (Biblical figure)</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:196804:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:196804:1"/>
            <p>THE FIRST MAN, <hi>OR,</hi> A Short Discourse OF ADAMS STATE: <hi>VIZ.</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Of his being made a living Soul.</item>
                  <item>2. Of the manner of his Fall.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>J.G.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Benjamin Allen</hi> in Popes-head-Alley, <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1643.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:196804:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:196804:2"/>
            <head>Adam <hi>a living Soul.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat is a living soul?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A living soul is Man in innocency: The Scripture saith, <hi>the first man was made a living soul; Adam</hi> was perfect in reason, knowing all naturall things in the fulnesse of their nature, worth and excellency, observing and taking pleasure in the glory of God, which did shine in through, and over all the works of the most high: So that there was not any beauty or vertue in any thing, but he had the sence and summe of it within his owne Capacity or reason. He gave names to Creatures suitable to their natures, strength and vivasity; Moreover he knew the beauty of things in their seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall causes, how they were knit together, and how this Union made a goodly Harmony; and although there were many things in nature contrary to each other, and considered in themselves, would destroy each other: Yet as they were ordered by the wisdome of the wisest, did unanimously agree with, and helpe each other. All things then were good both in themselves and in their severall effects: He knew no weaknesse or death in any thing, untill death first fell upon him, and then issued forth from him in, and upon all other Creatures. Hee knew himselfe to bee the chiefest of the way of God, and that God had more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect to him then to any of all his creatures (I speak compara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively) so that there was nothing that could gaine upon him, or rob him of his heart that was without him. Put all things to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether without him, and all will scarse prove equall to him, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for beauty, wisdome or heavenly knowledge; he knew God to be the upper ground of all things, both in their beings
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:196804:3"/>and motions; And if there was any excellency in any of the creatures (as in all there was some) it was the scatterings of the same breath which breathed first life in him. As the light and beames of the Sun are guides to conduct our eyes to the seat and throne of the Sun, where it is in its being beauty and full form; so were all creatures as so many severall lights and beams of the glory of God to convey <hi>Adam</hi> to the Throne of the high, full and beautifull Majesty, in whom he knew all things did concen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre.</p>
            <p>Doubtles he knew all things were borne up by the same arme which first gave them their beings, and he which gave them their beings, (I meane the Creatures) must be greater in being then they all, neither could they flourish any longer, then by the fulnesse and efficacy of that mighty being, they were repleni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed sutable to the greatnes and glory of the things which are seen, must things be which doth not appeare. And if the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then (as <hi>Paul</hi> saith) knew God in his invisible eternall power and Godhead: Surely <hi>Adam</hi> in these things knew more then they all, for if they who had severall broken pieces of reason weakly joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned together, and yet understood these things: doubtles he that was upright and had reason perfected, knew much more. God made man upright (saith the Scripture) I conceive the meaning of that word may be either.</p>
            <p>First, this with his heart fixed and placed onely upon God: vvhich way soever he turned himselfe, or upon whatsoever hee looked, all that he took pleasure to see, was god in all, mans mind at the first was upward, now downward</p>
            <p>Or secondly, the Word is a Metaphor, taken from a line or rule by which men measure or square out any particular worke, which rule they ought not to exceed. So man had then his bounds and limits beyond which he ought not to have passed, and in this compasse might have walked with pleasure.</p>
            <p>Or thirdly, It is set in opposition to crookednes: Man in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocency went not awry but passed straight forwards in the most pleasant paths, neither turning to the right, or the left hand. But now he leaves the straight line, and walks in waies contrary to truth, righteousnesse and peace, oft times striving how he may be most crooked and most froward, reeling to and fro like one drunke. The Scripture makes mention of a living soule: and a
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:196804:3"/>quickening spirit. <hi>Adam</hi> to be the one, and <hi>Christ</hi> to be the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. I shall endeavour according to my light, to shew the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of both. First for a living soule.</p>
            <p>The first and lowest meaning I conceive is this, to be a living soule, is to be truly a Man: Other creatures when they were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, were said to have life in them, but none besides Man, were said to be living soules.</p>
            <p>Secondly, a living soul is a man indeed, with a lively and act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ive principall of reason, by vertue whereof he was able to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinguish of things according to their worth and excellency and also fild with wisdome, whereby he saw how all causes by their severall influences and operations came to be most excellently united, and that the first cause which gave life and breath to all the rest, was not onely <hi>primum mobile,</hi> but also <hi>summum bonum,</hi> so that as his reason served him to couple all things together, so it also raised him to see how all things were coupled, and that he who did thus unite all, and overshadow all, by the influence and power of his eternall being was more glorious and great then they all, which considered, caused him there to rest, and in that to take full content.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, a living soul signifieth (as it hath reference to that estate in which he was thus upright) immutability and duration, and He (meaning God) breathed in him the breath of life. This breathing or breath of God, was the great power and glory of God, moulding of him into that glorious estate, and preserving of him in that estate, untill he left it, or rather that left him, of which I shall speak more hereafter.</p>
            <p>There was not the least tincture of death, that came upon man whiles he remained in this estate, neither in his body or minde, mortality was the consequence of sinne; If thou eatest saith the Scripture, in dying thou shalt dye: Whilest that he obeyed he was fresh, faire, and flourishing, without any defect, as all things else were. O! how goodly a thing was man untill he tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from <hi>Ish</hi> to <hi>Adam</hi> life was his being; yea, life was the flowre of his being, declaring him glorious untill death entred in, and diminished the powers of life.</p>
            <p>But because it lyes in my way; I will speak but briefly of this second thing, leaving it to its due place, I meane Christ a quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ening spirit.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:196804:4"/>
            <p> There are three things also to be considered for the opening of this: First, a quickening spirit is such a one, who must have the fulnesse and substance of all shadowes and outward appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rances in him. Spirit signifies the perfection and beauty or any thing. The other word put to it makes thus much, namely, this perfection and beauty in its alitude and vivasity, for nothing can be higher, more ample, or more lovely in being, then things tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly spirituall, or the spirit, the cause of spirituall things. Life is in Christ, because the power of the infinite and eternall being, dwells compleatly in him: One of the highest names which Christ himselfe sets forth God by, is this, that he is a Spirit, and Christ is this God spiritually understood.</p>
            <p>Secondly, a quickening spirit is one who hath not onely this in himselfe, but he hath power to convey this spirituall beauty upon whomsoever he will. The Sunne quickneth whom he will saith the Scripture, he can (by the mighty operation of his life and spirit) transforme all into the Image of the same glory if he will. Although <hi>Adam</hi> had life in him, (such a life as I have spoken of) yet had he not any power to convey the least dram of this life to any: Which doth manifest, that this life was much lower and weaker then that life which was in Christ.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the third meaning is this, that he is appointed and set a part of God for this end: the Scripture saith, he was made a quickening spirit, as Christ is God, so it is no robbery for him to be equall with God: and so he is neither under command, neither in that consideration doth he stand in need of any cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tesie or dignity from the God-head, but as he is <hi>God</hi> in our nature, cloathed with humane flesh, so is he set apart by the authority of the eternall Father to severall offices, by vertue whereof hee doth convey grace, knowledge and all divine priviledges and spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall blessings upon the Sonnes of men because there is no power in us of our selves, to bring life and divine strength to us: therefore God hath appointed an infallible meanes near him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe, which is able to conduce to the uttermost of that end; the happinesse of a poore dead soule laden with sinne and guilt, is this, that Christ is designed by the Father to quicken and raise him, and in all things it is his care to manifest himselfe faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:196804:4"/>
            <head>The manner or way of the fall of Adam.</head>
            <p>It is a great question, <hi>How Adam fall?</hi> That he is fallen is out of question, but the manner and way of his Fall is that which is much disputed, and seemes to be a great mystery: All conclude he was upright for a season, and as long as hee thus continued death and mortality entred not upon him.</p>
            <p>The thing first to bee considered is, Whether hee had this breath of life or uprightnesse (of which I have already spoken) of, in, and by himself, or by any other means. There is none will say, of himselfe; for he neither had his being, neither his well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>being of himselfe: for the Scripture saith, <hi>God formed him of the dust,</hi> and, <hi>God breathed in him the breath of life:</hi> If from God, the Question is, whether he had it absolutely, or by way of depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence. By absolute, I meane, whether hee had it so inherently established in him, as that by the keeping or losing of it (I meane in that consideration) he had no relation to God. If you will say he had it thus established in himselfe, then what is become of that Maxime, both of heathen Writers, of religious Writers, and of the Scriptures, that <hi>We live, move, and have our being in God?</hi> Surely if God without a helper made all things of nothing, then by the same power that all things were made, they must be every moment upheld and preserved, or else all things once againe would turne into nothing: and if all things, then <hi>Adam</hi> and the things of <hi>Adam</hi> (for he was one of the things that was made:) or further, if God had given this power to <hi>Adam</hi> wholly from himselfe, either there were at once two Gods, and so conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently no God, or else God had ungodded himselfe to make <hi>Adam</hi> a God, which were high blasphemy once to thinke. If I know any thing of God, this is one thing that I know, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though God is most excellent and full of goodnesse, so that his goodnesse is communicated and spread abroad, in, and over all things, yet doth he not absolutely part from any piece of his glory and goodnesse, so as that hee doth leave the managing thereof alone to any creature. The beames and heat of the Sun refresheth and strengtheneth many a Creature, and yet take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way the Sun from the beames thereof, and the beames will lose both their vertue and being and creatures their comfort. So
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:196804:5"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:196804:5"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:196804:6"/>there is much of the sweetnesse, goodnesse, and glory of God in many a Creature, as so many beames issuing forth from the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God; but take away God from these Creatures, they will lose their sweetnesse, their glory, and their very being also. It is a generall Tenet held by the major part of men, yea and good men also, whom I love and honour, here in England, That <hi>Adam</hi> had a power, in, and of himselfe to stand in that estate wherein he was created: (I should be sorry if by mistake I should wrong any, confident I am that I have heard some reason for it.) If he had power (I meane of himselfe) to stand, whence came it to passe he fell? Is there any desire of evill in good, or misery in happinesse: His standing was good, and doubtlesse so was the power by which he stood, whether it was in himselfe or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise; reason will tell us, (and as I have said <hi>Adam</hi> had the height of reason) so long as man keepes his reason, which brings him to felicity, he cannot presse after misery. It is said he had power to stand or fall; I conceive so long as he stood he had a power by which he stood; when he fell it was because hee wanted this power: if he had kept the power, or rather, the power had kept him, hee had never fallen; hee could not have power to fall (I meane in that estate which we call innocency) for falling from a good estate to a bad is through a defect of power. If <hi>Adam</hi> fell from life to death from felicity to misery, it was not because he had a power to fall but because his power failed him. It is true, whilest he stood he stood, and he stood by a power, and had not that power failed him he would have stood longer: but suppose it be objected, that the power by which hee was assaulted was greater then that which in that estate he was possessed withall, and so by that meanes he disobeyed; for saith the Man, <hi>The wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man which thou gavest me, gave mee of the tree, and I did eat:</hi> unto which I shall thus first answere, If we consider him before hee was fallen, or before the very act of his fall, the power which was against him was not equall to that which hee had: For if <hi>Adam</hi> knew God, and served God, (his desires and inclinations being onely thereunto, accounting this his greatest good, know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him to be most excellent, and his will to be most delighted in all this arising from a principle of knowledge and perfection which he had) then how can a lye be greater then truth, when truth is strong, yea strongest of all: the Divell he comes to him
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:196804:6"/>vvith this lye in his mouth, <hi>If thou doest disobey thou shalt live and be as God,</hi> and vvith such like vvords: <hi>Adam</hi> considered in that estate might thus have ansvvered the Divell (and his princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples vvould have led him to it) I knovv vvhat God hath said is true, he is God, and cannot deny himselfe, hee hath laid his command upon me, and given mee bounds beyond vvhich I may not goe; if thou saist othervvise, thou hast lost thy knovvledge of God, in vvhom all goodnesse and blessednesse consisteth, and art become a Lyer. It is true, that the Divell is said to be great and to have povver, and so is sinne also, but it is in reference to our vveake estate, vvhen vvee compare him and his povver vvith things truly good, hee hath no povver at all: indeed he vvould have the things vvhich are not, to be; and the things vvhich are, to lose their beings: but he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a deceiver is still deceived: untill <hi>Adam</hi> vvas deceived, hee never thought as the Divell did, and had his povver remained vvith him he never had been deceived; for as long as he stood it vvas the povver that kept him. I confesse if <hi>Adams</hi> estate vvas partly good and partly evill, then (if vve may use such an expression) he had power to fall: But if it vvas vvholly good, as the Scripture saith, that God savv all things vvhich he had made, <hi>and it was good;</hi> and doubtlesse men was one of the greatest of these good things, if not the greatest of all: then in that condition he could not have any inclination to evill, but his inclination to evill was his fall; so that we see <hi>Adams</hi> estate was wholly good, and in every good thing so long as it is good, it is by a power kept in its goodnesse. If <hi>Adam</hi> had the breath of life breathed in him, then so long as that breath of life remained in its glory, death could not enter upon him.</p>
            <p>But I shall secondly thus answer: If wee consider <hi>Adam</hi> ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther after his fall, or in his fall, (that is to say, as he did fully) the power against him was greater then that which vvas with him, otherwise he would not have fallen. If <hi>Adam</hi> was enve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomed with evill (as he vvas) the Devill was the envenomer, aad the cause is greater then the effects, although many times the effect doth exceedingly open, and give light to the nature of the cause. The Devill is a fountaine of lyes and deceipts, and by his subtilty in lying, filled <hi>Adam</hi> with deceipt. It is
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:196804:7"/>much to be thought, that in all the Devils words w<seg rend="sup">ch</seg> he used to deceive both <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Evah,</hi> we heard not of a word of repsy to gainsay his discourse: Indeed <hi>Evah</hi> tells him of the obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and band that God had laid upon them, but when hee chargeth God with falshood, and hatred, and the like we read not of any reply to cleare God, made by them, but rather a full entertaining of his discourse; by which I conceive, that no sooner were these motions suggested to them by the Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter but forthwith were they entertained by them; yea, and haply without any debate, whether they were right or wrong, good or evill: had they retained their knowledge and strength whilest they were under the temptation, they had then easily freed themselves from the efficacy of the temptation: but it seemes to me, whilest they were a tempting, or when they were tempted, the power departed from them, and so the temptation had efficacy upon them, otherwise they would have resisted the temptation. Oft times the act of evill, and the act of good, is performed with equall delight, although the consequence prove various: So haply whilst they were in the act of sinne, they knew it not, but afterwards the guilt and the shame which followed caused them to know: If ever the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill did shew himselfe like an Angel of light in any of his wiles, as oft he doth, surely one of the fairest dresses hee put on, was when hee tempted <hi>Adam; Ye shall be as Gods,</hi> saith the Tempter: it was not altogether so grosse as to tell him hee should be in Gods roome although it wanted but a step to it, for to be equall, is to divide, and to divide is to destroy; for to seeke to have two Gods at once, is to seeke to have none at all. Perhaps the Divell tooke the same method with <hi>Adam,</hi> to bring him to misery, as he himselfe practised when hee first wrought his owne misery.</p>
            <p>But to hover no longer, we see <hi>Adam</hi> hath lost his integri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and the man in that case is undone; How shall we find out the way of his losse? This I shall endevour to doe by discour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing upon two things; the first is. <hi>How, or from whence</hi> Adam <hi>had his power to stand?</hi> the second is, <hi>How he lost it?</hi> For the first of these I shall speake more briefe, because I have spoken of it already: All power is from the highest power, which is from
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:196804:7"/>God, from whence <hi>Adam</hi> had his; yet not so as that God par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from it out of his owne hand, for then it would have lost its power, and have been no power at all: Divide the streames from the fountaines, and they will quickly lose their natures and their names too; the power which with-held him was a momentary supply from God, which whilest he stood firme, kept him as firme as he was when first he had his being. He at the first was formed after the image of God, every minute was that image preserved and kept in him by the same power which fashioned it in him: The image of a thing is the repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sentation of the thing, although it is not the thing it selfe: <hi>Adam</hi> was formed after the image of God, this image was a description or draught of the glory of God upon him, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though (I confesse) not so glorious as that draught which is drawne forth upon Christ; for so farre as heaven in its glory is beyond the earth in its glory, so farre is the glory of Christ beyond the glory of <hi>Adam.</hi> For what saith the Scripture? <hi>the first man is of the earth, earthly; the second is the Lord from heaven:</hi> this image of God in <hi>Adam</hi> was the truth or spirit of his life, and life cannot bee maintained lively without some spring: The fountaine or spring which maintaines all true beings, is God, so that we may (I suppose) conclude that God gave him his life, and the same God did keep it, so long as it was kept.</p>
            <p>The second Question is, <hi>How</hi> Adam <hi>lost his integrity?</hi> And here (I confesse) I should be sorry to speak any thing contrary to reason or Religion; yet if I should miscarry, I should bee glad to be informed: and above all things, when I am speak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the things of God, I am most afraid of dishonouring or charging him with folly: For, <hi>let God be true and every man a lyer.</hi> But now I have begun to speake, I shall freely deliver my thoughts. Thus I thinke he lost it. As I have said, it was God that did uphold him whilest he stood, so it was the same God that did withdraw or kept back the power, and so <hi>Adam</hi> fell. Had he kept the power or rather the power kept him, he had not fallen; but God was pleased, for the magnifying of his name, to withdraw himselfe from him, and so left him under the power of the temptation, by which he was overcome. It
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:196804:8"/>was the power, or <hi>God</hi> that made him strong, and had this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued with him, he could not have been weak, and the Divill might have assaulted him long enough with all the power and subtilty he could get together, and all his batteries had bin in vaine, had but the same strength by which he was preserved, still remained with him. So now here wee see <hi>Adam</hi> almost in a moment high and low, rich and poore, strong and weake, happy and miserable, his glory and fence is gone, and left in the hands of cruell enemies, and these exercising tyranny up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him and tryumphing over him. But there are some Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections which rise up against what I have said: One is to this effect <hi>Whether in so saying we make not God the Author of sinne?</hi> For thus saith the Objection. <hi>If God withdraw or withhold himselfe from</hi> Adam, <hi>and the Divill come up against him</hi> (hee being now weake) <hi>is necessitated to yeeld, and to sinne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this I answer, that in a positive and strict sence he is not, for as of all things he is most cleare and free from finne in himselfe, and in his owne nature, there being no uncleanesse or uncleane thing that can enter into his Tabernacle, so is he as free and cleare, concerning the acting or working any evill, either in or by himselfe: for how can any uncleane thing come forth of the thing that is cleane. Sinne is not in him, therefore he cannot act or commit sinne. The Divill is positively evill, sinne dwells inherently in him, and is engrafted into his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: It was his action and motion which had an influence up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Adam,</hi> by vertue whereof he was drawne into the same condemnation with himselfe, and did actually as well as the Divill commit sinne: So that as concerning the temptation or working of sinne in <hi>Adam,</hi> God is altogether cleare, and to be discharged and the Divill and <hi>Adam</hi> himselfe to be blamed. If God gave <hi>Adam</hi> a Law, and this Law was good as all things else were then, and the goodnesse of the Law was either in its own nature, or because God gave it, God being the highest good cannot diminish or destroy the least good which he would have done, had he broken his owne Law. It is one thing to take away a power which is in it selfe good, or to take away a pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er by which any good thing is preserved, and it being taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, of necessity the good thing must perish; And it is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:196804:8"/>thing to commit sinne, and manifestly to act it, when the power which kept the good thing, and the good thing it selfe, which was kept by the power, are both departed To be an author of any thing, is to be a worker or actor of the thing, or else (which is higher) to give being to the thing. God is the author of all good or goodnesse, either as all good or goodnesse is concentered in him, or as all good is wrought and brought to light by him, therefore God cannot be the Author of sinne, I meane in a full and strict sence, because sinne hath not its being in him, he did not beget it, neither doth he cherish it in his bosome. Sinne is a deprivation or lessening of good, therefore it cannot be in God, because he is not only good, but good in the highest degree, saith the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, <hi>Sinne is of the Divill, and if of and from the Divill, then not of and from God:</hi> So that wee see the Divill may sinne, and <hi>Adam</hi> may sinne, and yet God not to be the author of sinne.</p>
            <p>But in the second place, I thus answer, that in an acciden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall way God may be said to occasion sinne, for had it bin the good pleasure of God to have given <hi>Adam</hi> the same power al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies, by which at first he stood in his integrity, he had not sinned. When the light is gone darknesse will cover the face of the earth, and the lights departure is occasionally the cause of darknesse, so is the departure of God from <hi>Adam,</hi> occasion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally the cause of his fall. Our Saviour saith, he came not to bring peace, but a sword, and yet the Angells saith, at his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming into the World, on earth peace, good will towards men; the truth is, our Saviour came to bring peace in plaine and strict sence, and that was the end of his comming, and yet occasionally came a sword. There are many things done in the World which are sinfull, which actions God hath a spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall hand in, and yet God is cleare from the evill of those actions: Suppose one man kill another with a Sword, here is God first permitting such an action, otherwise it could not be done, for if he pleased he could hinder it.</p>
            <p>And secondly, here is God giving power to the man, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by his action is done. If he puts forth his hand, if he strikes the stroke, it is by a power, if you will say it is by the power of nature, I will answer, that it is the God of nature gives na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture its power.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:196804:9"/>
            <p> Nay, thirdly, here is God accomplishing some end in this businesse, here is either some Judgement shewne upon the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son, or some example given for caution to the world; and yet God is free from the envy mischiefe, and evill of the acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Surely if God can free himselfe from evill in actions of this nature, (wherein so much of him is to be seen) wee may easily acquit him, when he doth out with hold that power, by which we are kept from sinning or evill actions. Many things that may occasion sinne, may be wholly free from sinne it self, unlesse it be in the occasion or accident (had I better expressi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for the present in my thoughts, then the word occasion, I would speak it:) Suppose a beautifull woman passeth by in the streets perhaps her heart is wholly and heavenly, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise she is very intent about the businesse in which she is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed; some man looketh upon her, and lusteth after her: She thinks not in the least degree of this busines; I hope every knowing man will free this woman from the evill of this acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. So God may occasion evill and yet be free, yea farre from the evill it selfe, the raine falls not for a long space upon the earth, in the meane time the earth parcheth and waxeth dry, and the grasse withereth; I hope none will say that the raine parched the ground, or withered the grasse. To conclude this first <hi>Objection.</hi> If God will withdraw, <hi>Adam</hi> must sinne, and yet <hi>Adam</hi> is the sinner and God cleare from his sinne.</p>
            <p>The second <hi>Objection</hi> (of which I shall speake more brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly) is; <hi>Whether God be not the originall cause of sinne?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this I answer no except I am mistaken in the word <hi>Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall;</hi> To be the originall cause of any thing is (I conceive) to be the first cause in giving the thing its being and denominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and such a cause, as that the thing which is the effect must pertake of the nature of the Cause, we oft times are speaking of the bewailing of our originall sinne wee meane that sinne which <hi>Adam</hi> had originally, or as the fountaine in him he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the stock from whence so many withered leaves and bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of impiety doth appeare in us. It was in him, it spread forth upon all mankind from him; The fountaine is the ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall of the streams, why, because the streams were first in the fountaine: God giveth not sinne a being, and yet without
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:196804:9"/>God sin could not be: happily to some it may appeare strange, yet in my thoughts it doth appeare true; I meane thus, God gives not sinne a being as he gave life to <hi>Adam,</hi> he breathed life in <hi>Adam,</hi> and then he lived. <hi>God</hi> breaths not, or works not sin in any, his breathings are pure and undefiled, all things unto which he doth positively give being from his owne workings are good, and I meane thus, when I say without <hi>God</hi> sinne could not be, either that it is his pleasure that sinne should have a being, otherwise he could have prevented it: Or else that hee suffers it; or else that he makes way for its being, which in a sence, yea and in a true sence he doth, for sinne had not been amongst men, had <hi>Adam</hi> stood: <hi>Adam</hi> could not stand when the power by which he stood was taken from him, and he as<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saulted; and it was <hi>God</hi> kept back the power by which he stood: if reason or Religion, or both would teach me to make <hi>God</hi> a lesser cause of sinne, were it for his honour, I should gladly do it, for above all things I desire to honour <hi>God; God</hi> is original<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly good and originally the cause of good and therefore cannot be originally the cause of evill; evill and good is at the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test longitude one from the other. Whilest <hi>Adam</hi> did well <hi>God</hi> was near unto him, but when he sinned he thrust <hi>God</hi> from him by his sinning.</p>
            <p>The third Objection is this.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>How God will be cleared to be righteous and just in his dealing to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards</hi> Adam, <hi>in the withdrawing of himselfe, when there was no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther means for him to be kept in his integrity?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this I answer.</p>
            <p>That <hi>God</hi> can doe no unjust thing, whatsoever hee doth is righteous, as he himselfe is righteous; All his works are by and from himselfe. The Potter hath power to make and designe his Vessells for honour or dishonour, at his pleasure, because they are his workmanship. If the Potter is to make these Ves<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sells by the commandement and power of some other; hee is to doe according to his Commission; But if he doth it with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out command and is left to his will, who is then to contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict him in what shape soever he maketh these Vessells or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to what use so ver he putteth them? So if <hi>God</hi> be under any higher command then himselfe, and had from that power a
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:196804:10"/>command to make <hi>Adam</hi> in that forme which he did, and to keep him continually in that forme and state wherein he was made then if he withdrew the power which kept <hi>Adam</hi> in this estate (as he did) he had done unrighteously, and must have bin accomptable to him from whom he had the command. But <hi>God</hi> is above all Law, there is none above him to compell him to doe any thing or to give him a Law, unto which he might owe subjection; neither is there any equall to him, whereby he might be intreated, therefore he is become a Law to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe he measures out all his wayes and actions by the line and rule of the god-head. As there is none but himselfe to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell himselfe to the doing of any action, so neither doth hee aske advice of any but himselfe for the performance of the same. What he wills is a Law, and if he wills any thing, the thing he wills is according to knowledge, wisdome and judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and he seeth and judgeth all things according to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of his owne nature and being, which is according to truth, yea according to the highest truth. It is a Maxime ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall and true, that <hi>God</hi> is the highest being, and perfection it selfe, that he is without addition or diminution, if so, let him do what he will, he cannot erre or do unrighteously. If he is one huge piece of spirituall glory, and all things in him are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite, as he himselfe is, in beauty, prayse and perfection, how is it possible to thinke he can doe any uncomely thing; if he had pleased he might have made <hi>Adam</hi> in another forme, either higher or lower at his pleasure, and who should have contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted him. If he will make his creatures glorious, and suffer them to be blasted immediatly, that so he may bring in a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter glory to make himselfe more glorious: Who shall controle him, this is the weaknes of man, that because wee by our low and weak judgement and reason cannot finde out the high <hi>God</hi> in the way of his righteousnesse: Therefore will we seek to make him unrighteous, when we should rather (like <hi>Paul</hi>) who speaking of the great way of <hi>God</hi> in shutting up all men under unbeliefe) cry out that his Judgements are unsearchable, and his wayes past finding out. All unrighteousnesse ariseth from some defect and unevennesse in mens wayes, if <hi>Gods</hi> way was not compleat nay if this his worke in the leaving of <hi>Adam</hi> to himselfe, was not glorious and admirable; or if wee can tell
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:196804:10"/>of any that will come after him, and rectifie or amend his worke, then he will confesse his fault, and to him owe the tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute of praise. Is it possible, to be thought, that he which knoweth all things at once, which shall be throughout eternity and by the same wisdome and knowledge ordereth the being, the forme of the being, the time of the being of every thing which shall be, should doe any thing contrary to himselfe, and if he doth nothing contrary to himselfe, hee cannot doe any thing unrighteously, because as I have said, he is a law to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe? It is a true rule, that where there is no Law, there is no transgression, then if there is none to be a Lawgiver to God, and his knowledge and will, are the rule by which he measures out all things; who then can say what he doth is done amisse, although he doth whatsoever he will.</p>
            <p>But secondly, I thus answer, That God was not any way en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged to keep <hi>Adam</hi> in that estate wherein he was first created: Had he been engaged to keep him, he must have kept him. If God had made <hi>Adam</hi> any promise, that as he had created him righteous, so hee would still keepe him in his righteousnesse, God must then have regarded his promise, otherwise hee would have been unrighteous; <hi>Adam</hi> could challenge nothing at his hands, because he promised nothing to him: there is two things that doe principally binde, either a <hi>Law,</hi> or a <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise;</hi> there was neither of these upon God, to tye him to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve <hi>Adam</hi> in that estate wherein he first created him. Doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lesse <hi>Adam</hi> in that had been happy, had God said thus to him, As I have made thee righteous, and beautified thee with mine image, so I will for ever keep thee: the reason is this, God cannot change or deny himself, he is faithfull if he saith any thing, he knoweth he must effect the thing which he hath spo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, therfore he is wise &amp; carefull in all his sayings: when God speaketh any thing, he speaketh it of himselfe, therefore hee must needs speake the truth, and he is as carefull to performe what he speaketh, as he is to speake it, otherwise he would not deale truly. One great difference betweene the estate of <hi>Adam</hi> and the estate of one in Christ Jesus, is this That to such which are in Christ Jesus he hath engaged himselfe by Covenant and Promise, that he will also keepe them in Christ: and this is
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:196804:11"/>cleare that he never failed any in the performing of his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise; but he did not so to <hi>Adam.</hi> Indeed he gave him a Law, and bid him keepe it, but he did not tell him he would helpe him to keepe it: the case is much alike betwixt the condition of <hi>Adam,</hi> and such who are under the Law, and looke for hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinesse by it; men might have been happy that were under the Law, could they have kept it, but the Law could not give of it selfe life neither could those that were subject to it keep it: so <hi>Adam</hi> could not keepe that Law unto which he was subject, neither was there life or power in that Law to keepe him. What is to be said? God might very well blame, yea, and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish <hi>Adam</hi> for the breach of his Law, because he was his Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, and was above him; yea, and under that consideration he ought God his very being; but <hi>Adam</hi> had not wherewithall to charge God, but must lay his hand upon his mouth and be silent. By this we may see, that God doth not onely manifest himselfe to be righteous in the withdrawing himselfe from <hi>Adam,</hi> but even by it his righteousnesse doth shine abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly.</p>
            <p>The next Objection is this, <hi>That God did command impossibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties;</hi> For thus saith the Objection, <hi>If God gave</hi> Adam <hi>such a Law, which he knew he had not power to keep, how then could hee looke for obedience to that Law, which was impossible for him to obey?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I answer affirmiatvely, that <hi>God</hi> may if he please, command things impossible for men to doe, <hi>God</hi> is the Soveraigne <hi>Lord,</hi> and as it is his Prerogative Royall to make and give Lawes, so by the same Prerogative may he make what Lawes he will: He may bid me doe what he pleaseth. and lay a penaltie upon mee if I doe not the thing that pleaseth him, yea, and execute the penaltie also, and yet remaine just and righteous. The reason is, because he is Soveraigne or chiefe, there is none to sit in Counsell with him when he maketh or ordaineth Lawes, or to controle him by saying, let them be thus or thus: Therefore what he wills is a Law, and that he wills is good; And if hee wills a Lavv impossible for man to keep yet this is a goo Law, he is our Creator, he gave us our beings, and the forme of our beings, had he pleased he might have given us other kind of beings, and who could or durst controle him, and so might hee
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:196804:11"/>(if he pleased) dissolved our beings, and yet be as free from con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trole, and shall we allow him the greater and not the lesse. If God gave us our beings vvhich vvere good, and gave us a law in the keeping vvhereof wee might have kept our selves in this goodnes, and yet vve had not power to keep this Law: Did he not doe well? doubtles he did (or if he did not, then let us blame him) the Lawes vvhich <hi>God</hi> gave unto <hi>Moses,</hi> seems to me to be as hard to keep, as that which he gave to <hi>Adam</hi> in Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radise, for none hitherto have kept it: And you in your <hi>Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chise</hi> say: <hi>Is any man able to keep the Commandements?</hi> The An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer is no: And yet none either doth or durst blame the law, or the Lawgiver Surely if men do, and may command things impossible God may.</p>
            <p>There are many Lavves for the vvell being of a Kingdome or State (these being grounded on the word of God) which Kings and Governours make, and yet how few of these are there duly observed, nay by reason of our vveak and infirme estate it is impossible fully to keep them, and yet who blames either the Lawes, or the Lawmakers. Some have run (at least in my apprehension) into a strange absurdity, by denying this poin, tvvhich I am now speaking of, vvhich they have done by placing a povver in man to doe Gods Will or Command of himselfe, and in effect saying, that it is in the vvill of man to believe, to repent, and consequently to be a selfe Saviour. But to the matter in hand, our Saviour telleth the <hi>Jewes,</hi> that to worke the vvorke of <hi>God</hi> is to believe, and <hi>John</hi> telleth us, that the Commandement is Faith or believing. It appeareth Faith is a Commandement, and yet it is impossible for flesh and blood to believe, for saith the Scripture, It is the guift of God; so that wee may see, <hi>God</hi> did not onely command things im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possible for <hi>Adam</hi> to doe or performe, but also for all his poste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and yet he remaineth faithfull and just. There are many things vvhich <hi>God</hi> doth, vvhich in our eyes vvould seeme un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous, nay, inhumane and cruell and yet he is just in so do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>God</hi> bids <hi>Abraham</hi> sacrifice his Sonne, and it is plaine, if he had so done, he must have murthered his Sonne, and vvee know that in the Commandement, God saith, <hi>Thou shalt doe no murther:</hi> And yet vve may not say, that God did any unjust
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:196804:12"/>thing in the commanding or bidding of <hi>Abraham</hi> to observe such a command. If God then doth give a law, and yet doth bid men to doe things contrary to that Law (and yet doth no evill) why should it then seem a harsh thing to us if God gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth us such a Law which wee cannot fulfill or obey.</p>
            <p>Here are two things to bee considered about this busi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and I hope I shall not swerve from my Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course.</p>
            <p>The first is, whether <hi>Abraham</hi> had sinned if he had obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>God</hi> in the sacrificing of his Sonne <hi>Isaack</hi> or no? I conceive all without scruple will answer negatively.</p>
            <p>The second thing is, Whether God did any evill in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding any thing for <hi>Abraham</hi> to doe contrary to a former command?</p>
            <p>I answer, that God may repeale or call back any of his laws, if he pleaseth; Or else if he pleaseth bid any one do any thing contrary to any of his commands. The reason is this, because by all the Laws or Commands of God positive, wee are ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and engaged, and not God. If God bids us doe a thing, wee are to doe it. If by and by he bids us undoe that thing, or doe something contrary to it, we are still to doe it. A Master may bid a servant do a thing, and anon after bid him undoe it again, and yet the Servant is to obey his Master. So it is the Sover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aignty or Prerogative Royall, for God to command what hee will, and it is our duety to be obedient to that which he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands.</p>
            <p>Where God promiseth us any thing, then he is engaged, but not when he commands. When the <hi>Israelites</hi> were to depart out of <hi>Egypt</hi> God (not purposing that they should returne againe) God bids them borrow Jewels and Rayment of the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> and the <hi>Israelites</hi> never restored the things they borrowed to the <hi>Egyptians.</hi> And I also suppose that when <hi>God</hi> bids the <hi>Israe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lites</hi> thus to borrow it was not his intent they should pay them againe: And I doe bring these instances onely to possesse the Reader, that God by his Supremacie may command things for men in and of themselves, impossible to doe. If God bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth us believe in Jesus Christ, and by so doing wee shall have eternall life, yet it is as impossible of our selves to believe, as
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:196804:12"/>it is for us to make a World; Doth God doe well then in bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of us believe? if he doth well (as sure he doth) why doe we then complain, is not that which he wills excellent and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together to be desired: but suppose any one should thus object, that although God is Soveraigne Lord over all, and may by virtue of his Soveraignty command what he will yet whether or no he doth command any thing contrary to reason? So saith the Objection, to command impossibilities, is to command things unreasonable.</p>
            <p>First, I will answer,</p>
            <p>That there is a great difference between Gods reason (if I may use such an expression) and ours: Wee reason either car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, or at the best according to the Law of reason, or that reason which wee see in the Law, but Gods reason, or the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son in God, which moved him to give us a law, is either from himselfe, or else doth end in himselfe: the reason that was in God, to give us a Law is one thing, and the reason that is in that law, or that that the law works in us, is another, &amp; yet both helps to cleare God in this businesse, for if it be Gods reason to give us a Law, and his Law be good, and yet we through our unreasonablenes breake so reasonable a Law: I hope wee will neither blame God or his law. It is corrupt reason that vvill quarrell against the Will of God, true reason will never. If a Master doth command a Servant to doe any unreasonable thing, he doth ill, because he is to follow the Lavv of reason in all his Commands, but God cannot command any unrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonable thing, because his Will is the highest reason, there is reason in his law, and yet his Will is more reasonable (if wee may so speake) for the cause is greater then the effect, and his Will is the cause of his Law.</p>
            <p>But Secondly, True reason vvill helpe us to cleare God in this thing, and faith much more, reason vvill make God the highest cause, and not onely the highest cause, but also the ground and procurer of all causes and things whatsoever, and if so, then he must be Supreame Lord over all and if Supream, then reason will tell us, that he may command what hee will. Indeed if a Master command a Servant to doe things impossi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, he doth ill, because there is a command lyeth upon the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:196804:13"/>Master that he ought not to oppresse his Servant, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore reason will tell us that he doth ill, but there is no reason that can tell us, either that God is tyed to the observation of any particular command, or that he is limited or streightened in the commanding of such and such particular things beyond vvhich he ought not to passe: But true reason will tell us, that he may command vvhat hee vvill, and if hee command that vvhich doth please him, then is he just and righteous. If God can give himselfe a reason to satisfie himselfe, vvhy hee doth give such and such a Lavv, and if vve by reason can satisfie our selves, that if he please, he may give such a Lavv, then if hee be pleased why doe vve complaine; suppose <hi>God</hi> should com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand any man to make a vvorld (I onely put it by vvay of sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position) I vvould aske that man whether <hi>God</hi> doth vvell or no in so doing. I am confident when he commandeth men to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, he biddeth them doe a thing equivalent to the making of the World, for the works require one and the same power to bring forth these things to light: but wee are apt to quarrell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst God, because his waies are above our wayes, but if it were not so, how could he be <hi>God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wee may be brought higher and higher by degrees into the knowledge of the glory of God, and the surpassing excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of his eternall being: but it cannot be imagined, that hee should stoop below himselfe, to portray himselfe suitable to the modell of our carnall apprehensions.</p>
            <p>It is true God doth stoop low, but never below himselfe, for God to stoop low is this, that through the height of his good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse and grace he is pleased to discover somewhat of that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine and everlasting invisible excellence, which is treasured up within his owne brest▪ but to stoope below himselfe (I mean in a strict sence) is to loose the height of that goodnesse and grace, and to make himselfe appeare to be something that hee is not, which is not to be thought; For God cannot de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lude, which hee must doe, if hee should appeare to be that which hee is not: therefore if wee know that God speaketh thus and thus, or biddeth us doe such and such things, when
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:196804:13"/>wee by the weakenesse of our Capacity, cannot fathome his way; Let us sit downe and say O! how unsearchable is his wisedome, and his waies past finding out.</p>
            <p>Thus have I briefly treated about the nature of <hi>Adams</hi> fall, or the means and way by which hee came to fall: If I knew any other Objection of any concernment that might arise, I should endeavour to answer it.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>